Finding Aid for Hussein Makled papers, 1956-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hussein Makled papers 1956-1999
Makled, Hussein.
0.4 linear feet.
07115 Aa 2
Hussein Makled is a leader in the Arab American community of Southeastern Michigan, one of the founding members of the Islamic Center of America. The papers of Hussein Makled document his work as a leader of the Islamic Center of America and its predecessor organizations, as well as the career of Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Hussein Makled (donor no. 9928 ) in 2007.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Hussein Makled is a leader in the Arab American community of Southeastern Michigan, one of the founding members of the Islamic Center of America. Makled moved to Highland Park, Mich., from Lebanon in the 1940s because of the economic opportunities in Michigan. He joined the Hashmi Society, a mosque in Dearborn's South End, and soon convinced the scholar Mohamad Jawad Chirri, who he had known in Lebanon, to provide guidance to the society. Chirri became imam of the Hashmi Society, and Chirri and Makled, along with a group of young members, began raising money to build a proper mosque. After years of fundraising, which included a gift of over $40,000 from Egyptian president Gamal Abdel Nasser, ground was broken for the Islamic Center of Detroit in 1962. Makled remained active in the Center as it grew to become the Islamic Center of America and moved to a new mosque, dedicated in 2003, known as the largest mosque in North America.
The papers of Hussein Makled document his work as a leader of the Islamic Center of America and its predecessor organizations, as well as the career of Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri. The collection is divided into two series: Topical files and Photographs.
Subjects:
Arab Americans--Michigan.; Chirri, Mohamad Jawad.; Islamic Center of America (Dearborn, Mich.); Islamic Center Foundation Society.; Makled, Hussein.; Muslims--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Arab Americans--Michigan--Spiritual life.; Chirri, Mohamad Jawad.; Jackson, Jesse, 1941-; Iran.; Islamic Center of America (Dearborn, Mich.); Mosques--Michigan--Detroit.; Nasser, Gamal Abdel, 1918-1970.; Qāsim, Abd al-Karīm, 1914-1963.; Religious services--Michigan--Detroit.; Religious services--Iran.; Sadr, Mūsá.
Contributors:
Berry, Nabih.; Elahi, Mohammad Ali.; Nasser, Gamal Abdel, 1918-1970.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Topical files
  The Topical files series includes records of the Islamic Center Foundation Society, the organization that planned and raised funds for the building of the Islamic Center of Detroit. Of particular interest is a letter that accompanied Egyptian president Nasser's contribution to the center in 1959. The series also includes writings by and about Imam Chirri, along with one letter of Chirri's successor, Imam Mohammad Ali Elahi, describing the situation at the Center in 1994.
  - Berry, Nabih, essay re Mohamad Jawad Chirri (Box 1)
  - Chirri, Mohamad Jawad, essay re Five schools of Islamic jurisprudence (Box 1)
  - Elahi, Mohammad Ali, letter re Islamic Center of America (in Farsi), 1994 (Box 1)
  - Islamic Center Foundation Society
    - Constitution (Box 1)
    - Correspondence re donation from Gamal Abdel Nasser, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence re Swiss bank account, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence miscellaneous, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Financial records, 1956-1960 (Box 1)
    - Financial records, 1960-1970, 4 volumes (Box 1)
    - Financial reports, 1962 and 1966 (Box 1)
    - Financial miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Islamic Center of Detroit, board members, ca. 1965 (Box 1)
  - Islamic Center of America, correspondence and other documents, 1990-1995 (Box 1)
  - Islamic Services, Inc., 1994 (Box 1)
  - Ismail, Vehbi, pamphlet owned by (Box 1)
  - Makled, Hussein, essay re Mohamad Jawad Chirri (Box 1)
  - Makled, Hussein, essay re history of Islamic Center (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The photograph series contains photos relating to the Islamic Center mosque built in 1962 and 1963 and to the career of Imam Chirri. Photos are included of Chirri with various Islamic and world leaders, among them Jesse Jackson, Gamal Abdel Nasser, Abdul Karim Qassem, and Moussa al-Sadr, along with photos of Chirri leading Friday prayers in Iran in 1979.
  - Chirri, Mohamad Jawad (Box 1)
  - Iran, Chirri leading Friday prayers, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Islamic Center of America (Box 1)